<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/dummies/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/dummies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-12-18T17:42:35-05:00</updated><id>/dummies/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Music theory from dummies</title><subtitle>Talk about. Pop music talk about.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ya gotta look sharp</title><link href="/dummies/melody/2022/12/18/ya-gotta-look-sharp.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ya gotta look sharp" /><published>2022-12-18T14:30:12-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-18T14:30:12-05:00</updated><id>/dummies/melody/2022/12/18/ya-gotta-look-sharp</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dummies/melody/2022/12/18/ya-gotta-look-sharp.html"><![CDATA[<p>So far we’ve focused exclusively on rhythm, or how notes are arranged in time. We haven’t talked about pitch, which is how high or low a note sounds.</p>

<p>Sound is caused by waves of vibrating air. If you measure how fast the air wave is vibrating (how many vibrations per second), that’s called its <strong>frequency</strong> (in Hertz).</p>

<p>If you play the note A in the middle of a piano, for example, it produces a sound wave with a frequency of 440 Hz. Different keys produce waves with different frequencies, which is why they sound different. As you move from left to right on a piano, the note gets higher in pitch, and the frequencies correspondingly increase.</p>

<p>Pitches are identified by letters: A, B, C, D, E, F, and G. After G comes A again, and so on. We draw them on a set of five parallel horizontal lines called the <strong>staff</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/egbdf.png" alt="Staff with labeled pitches." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<p>Mnemonics are your friend. The spaces between the lines, from bottom to top, spell FACE. The lines themselves from bottom to top represent EGBDF (most commonly “Every Good Boy Deserves Fudge”).</p>

<p>On the piano, the letters A to G represent the white notes. They’re conventionally ordered starting on C: C, D, E, F, G, A, B, C.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/pianokeys.png" alt="Labeled piano keys." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<p>Some (but not all!) adjacent pairs of white keys have a black key between them. Each black key’s note has two names. For example, the note between C and D can be called “C-sharp” (notated C♯) or “D-flat” (notated D♭). Sharp means higher (e.g., C♯ is higher than C) and flat means lower.</p>

<p>On the staff, we put sharp or flat signs to the left of the note head. So this is C-sharp:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/8f3efc314e9ced1e511b1a29025ca578.svg" alt="C-sharp." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>These sharp and flat symbols are called <strong>accidentals</strong>.</p>

<p>An accidental sign modifies all instances of one note until the end of the measure. For example, in the first line of John Mayer’s On The Way Home:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/30991b1a0616e1baf3e91820d44b41a5.svg" alt="First measure of On the Way Home by John Mayer." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Here the first F (on the word “I”) is sharped. So you play F-sharp. Then the second note (“and”) is another F without a sharp symbol. You play F-sharp there, too, since sharp signs last until the end of the measure. Same for the first syllable of “architect.” The other non-F notes are not sharp.</p>

<p>One last symbol to know is ♮, pronounced “natural.” So C♮ is “C natural,” and it refers to a regular non-flat non-sharp C.</p>

<p>Why would you need to use a natural sign? Look at this measure from When I’m Sixty-Four:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/48a4d25f4f9bdbba42147daa49a270c6.svg" alt="Excerpt from When I'm Sixty-Four." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The first D (on “day”) is flat, and the second D (“greet”) is not flat. Without the natural sign, both Ds would be assumed flat.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="melody" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So far we’ve focused exclusively on rhythm, or how notes are arranged in time. We haven’t talked about pitch, which is how high or low a note sounds.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tie your mother down</title><link href="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/14/tie-your-mother-down.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tie your mother down" /><published>2022-11-14T08:55:07-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T08:55:07-05:00</updated><id>/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/14/tie-your-mother-down</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/14/tie-your-mother-down.html"><![CDATA[<p>There are a few common symbols that can change the written duration of a note.</p>

<h1 id="dots">Dots</h1>

<p>You may see a note head followed by a small dot. That’s called, <em>creatively</em>, a <strong>dotted</strong> note. A dotted note lasts 1.5 times as long as its non-dotted counterpart. E.g.: since a quarter note is one beat, a dotted quarter note is one and a half beats. A dotted eighth note is one and a half eighth notes, or three-fourths of a beat.</p>

<p>Here’s an example from The Word by The Beatles:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; 4 &amp;     | 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; 4 &amp;
lyric: So    fine    it's    sun   shine
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The first word, “so,” lasts for the count “1 and 2,” but doesn’t continue to the second “and.” That’s a duration of three eighth notes, or equivalently one and a half quarter notes. So you can write it as a dotted quarter note.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/31d4ff22d11ca92f00aeb13ce2529557.svg" alt="Dotted notes from The Word by The Beatles." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Rests can be dotted, too. This measure from Dirty Little Secret starts with a dotted quarter rest (1.5 beats).</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/a2fb2e4ec752aa291f6972e3d7f44835.svg" alt="Dotted rests in the verse of Dirty Little Secret." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Some of these notes extend across the measure boundaries. That’s what those curved lines are for.</p>

<h1 id="ties">Ties</h1>

<p>If you connect two note heads with an arc, the arc is called a <strong>tie</strong>. It’s played as a single note with the combined durations of the notes it connects. So if you tie together two eighth notes, they sound like a single quarter note. Here we tie an eighth note to a quarter note:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/9d420fd512daff9c5641ede7d8cf1da9.svg" alt="Bars from Dirty Little Secret illustrating a tie." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>A measure boundary (bar line) is the most common place to use a tie.</p>

<h1 id="things-wouldnt-be-so-confused">Things wouldn’t be so confused</h1>

<p>Let’s walk through the first two measures of the chorus of Linger by The Cranberries.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: 1   e   &amp;   a   2   e   &amp;   a   3   e   &amp;   a   4   e   &amp;   a   |   1   e   &amp;   a
vocal:                         but I'm i-          in          so          deep
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Try counting this out slowly. Usually I tap each sixteenth note on my fingers. I tap my index finger for each numeral, middle finger for “e,” ring finger for “and,” and pinky for “a.” Index, middle, ring, pinky. Over and over. Each tap is a sixteenth note and that helps me figure out where each note should be placed.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  beat: 1   e   &amp;   a   2   e   &amp;   a   3   e   &amp;   a   4   e   &amp;   a   |   1   e   &amp;   a
finger: 1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4   |   1   2   3   4
linger:                         but I'm i-          in          so          deep
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>There aren’t any notes sung until the second “&amp;.” So we start with a rest. It lasts for the full first beat, and half of the second beat. 1.5 beats = a dotted quarter rest.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/e4b2133acf123c6e81c2ed6d7cbd784d.svg" alt="A dotted quarter rest." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The first two words, “but I’m,” are each one finger-tap, or one sixteenth note. Picturesque.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/3f75fde363b1cfbeeb4ac4f0d5d4d835.svg" alt="First two notes of Linger." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The next word, “in,” is sung with two syllables. The first syllable lasts three finger-taps, which is three sixteenth notes.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  beat: 3   e   &amp;   a   4   e   &amp;   a
finger: 1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4
linger: i-          in          so   
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If it lasted <em>two</em> sixteenth notes, it’d be an eighth note. If it lasted <em>four</em> sixteenth notes, it’d be a quarter note. But it’s in between. It’s 1.5 eighth notes: a dotted eighth.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/f44f8e76a9fec4c72d232dd3684deafe.svg" alt="First 3 notes of Linger." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The second syllable of “in” lasts the same amount of time.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/547ff8db025612b40eb8f7c98aa7d09c.svg" alt="First 4 notes of Linger." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Then “so” is two finger-taps, or two sixteenth notes, or one eighth note. We can connect this non-dotted eighth note with the previous two dotted ones.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/a9d970f179120556617193666e05e9d2.svg" alt="First measure of Linger chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The word “deep” lasts an entire measure by itself, so we draw a whole note.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/bdfb26983406b2a920b153a1599299a5.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Linger chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Ain’t that satisfying?</p>

<h1 id="its-never-quite-as-it-seems">It’s never quite as it seems</h1>

<p>One last thing. Advanced extra credit addendum.</p>

<p>What’s shown above is a perfectly valid way to write this melody. But the dotted eighth notes are a little awkward. It takes some mental effort to keep track of where each downbeat falls. Especially beat 4, because there isn’t a note that starts on beat 4. The second syllable of “in” hits right before beat 4, and “so” hits right after, with “in” straddling the beat boundary.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>  beat: 3   e   &amp;   a   4   e   &amp;   a
finger: 1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4
linger: i-          in          so   
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>What we can do is break up this troublesome second syllable of “in.” We can separate it into the part before the downbeat (a sixteenth note), and the part on/after (an eighth note), and then connect them with a tie.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>                    this part is before the downbeat
                    |
                    *
  beat: 3   e   &amp;   a   4   e   &amp;   a
finger: 1   2   3   4   1   2   3   4
linger: i-          in          so   
                        *   *
                        |   |
                        ------------ this part is on/after the downbeat
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Check it out:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/329b64a5bb97a546aa84bba3c7bba98a.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Linger chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Now the third and fourth beats are neatly visually separated. With practice you’ll find that really helps readability.</p>

<p>If you didn’t follow that section, don’t worry about it. It comes naturally with time once you see enough of these. I just wanted to explain why you sometimes see a tie in the middle of a measure. It doesn’t really matter why as long as you can read it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There are a few common symbols that can change the written duration of a note.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The rest is still unwritten</title><link href="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The rest is still unwritten" /><published>2022-11-09T10:21:14-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-09T10:21:14-05:00</updated><id>/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten.html"><![CDATA[<p>So far we’ve been over how to notate note durations. We accomplished the dubious feat of reading the first two measures of the chorus to Dirty Little Secret by The All-American Rejects.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/d0055b815d31798f4035d0496ede7ebd.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The next measure has a pause before he starts singing again. That’s called a rest.</p>

<h1 id="rests">Rests</h1>

<p>Rest durations are divided the same way note durations are (whole rest, half rest, etc.). The symbols are annoying. Sometimes you can infer them from context clues.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/rest_values.png" alt="Diagram showing rest values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 150px;" /></p>

<p>The set of five horizontal lines, upon which all music is written, is called the <strong>staff</strong>.</p>

<p>The whole and half rest are distinguished by their position with respect to the staff line. The whole rest hangs down from the line, and the half rest pops up, like a top hat. “Half” shares two letters with “hat.” That’s the best I got.</p>

<p>So in the song, we now have a full measure without any notes (four beats, or a whole rest), followed by one quarter rest (one beat) before he starts singing again.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: | 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; 4 &amp; | 1 &amp; 2     &amp; 3    &amp; 4  &amp; |
vocal: |                 |     Don't   tell a-ny   |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Or, nicely typeset:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/af3f7c4022fd06ac466b5ede334542aa.svg" alt="Next 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Try tapping out the whole thing. It takes some mental effort at first but once it becomes automatic it’s very fun.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/c7ea4d05e744416296015a5641bc172e.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So far we’ve been over how to notate note durations. We accomplished the dubious feat of reading the first two measures of the chorus to Dirty Little Secret by The All-American Rejects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">They hold no quarter</title><link href="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="They hold no quarter" /><published>2022-11-06T10:52:58-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T10:52:58-05:00</updated><id>/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter.html"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re transcribing music, you need to express how long to hold
each note. That’s what rhythm notation is for.</p>

<p>The basic unit of note duration is called a “whole note.” The precise amount of time you hold a whole note depends on a few factors, but if the time signature is 4/4 (and it usually is), a whole note always lasts four beats. A half note is half as long as a whole note (2 beats), a quarter note is half as long as that (1 beat), etc.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-draw">How to draw</h1>

<p>The notation works like hangman: you start with a circle and then
draw more and more extra stuff on it.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/note_values.png" alt="Diagram showing note values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>The circle is called the <strong>note head</strong></li>
  <li>The stick attached to the circle is called a <strong>stem</strong></li>
  <li>The squiggle attached to the stem is called a <strong>flag</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>When you have consecutive notes with flags, it’s conventional to draw them connected together with straight lines (called <strong>beams</strong>).</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/beams.jpg" alt="Diagram showing note values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<h1 id="quarter-notes">Quarter notes</h1>

<p>In 4/4 time, if you tap your foot and count each beat, each tap is 
a quarter note. You can say it out loud while you tap: “1, 2, 3, 4.”</p>

<p>I’ll use Dirty Little Secret a lot because it’s such a simple melody.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: 1    2    3   4
vocal: I'll keep you my
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s how you’d formally draw that measure. The little “c” symbol means “common time” (4/4).</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/20d9593b349218e9dbed29e99e9801eb.svg" alt="First measure of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>A quarter note lasts for one beat, so each note in this measure is a quarter note.</p>

<h1 id="eighth-notes">Eighth notes</h1>

<p>If you divide each foot-tap in half, each half has a name:</p>
<ul>
  <li>the <strong>downbeat</strong>: when your foot is on the ground</li>
  <li>the <strong>upbeat</strong>: when your foot is off the ground</li>
</ul>

<p>You count these out loud by adding the word “and”: “1 and 2 and 3 and 4 and.” When you say that, each syllable is one eighth note. Each number is a downbeat, and each “and” is an upbeat.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: 1    &amp;   2   &amp;   3   &amp;   4   &amp;   | 1   &amp;   2   &amp;   3   &amp;   4   &amp;
vocal: I'll     keep    you     my        dir-ty  lit-tle se-     cret
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The first four words last 2 eighth notes each. That’s why they’re quarter notes. The syllables of “dirty little” are each half that length, so we write them as eighth notes.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/d0055b815d31798f4035d0496ede7ebd.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The last quarter note’s stem goes up instead of down, but the direction doesn’t matter. It just saves visual space to draw it that way, so the stem doesn’t stick way up above the line.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you’re transcribing music, you need to express how long to hold each note. That’s what rhythm notation is for.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We got the beat</title><link href="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We got the beat" /><published>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</published><updated>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</updated><id>/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat</id><content type="html" xml:base="/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html"><![CDATA[<p>A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is 
somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. 
It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: x    x    x   x  x      x       x  x
vocal: I'll keep you my dir-ty lit-tle se-cret
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A group of beats is called a measure (or, synonymously, a bar).</p>

<p>Most commonly, beats are grouped in groups of 4.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | x    x    x   x  | x      x       x  x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It’s rare for a hip hop song to use any grouping other than 4. 
A standard rap line spans one single four-beat measure, which 
is why rappers refer to lines as “bars.”</p>

<p>When the beats are grouped in fours, we say a song is “in 
4/4 time.” It’s pronounced “four-four” and it is not a fraction
even though it looks like one.</p>

<p>4/4 is an example of a “time signature.” A song’s time signature 
determines how its rhythm will be written. The top number 
indicates the number of beats in each measure. You can ignore 
the bottom number for now.</p>

<p>In 4/4 music with drums, it’s conventional to hit the snare on
beats 2 and 4. So locating the snare can help you get your bearings.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1    2    3   4  | 1      2       3  4    |
snare: |      x        x  |        x          x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>6/8 is the next most common time signature. It groups beats in sixes.
Think of Piano Man, or the verse of Lucy In The Sky.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1   2    3    4    5  6 | 1    2  3 4     5  6 |
vocal: | Pic-ture your-self in a | boat on a river      |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Other time signatures are much less common, so they tickle your
brain when you hear them. Pink Floyd’s Money is in 7/4. The main
riff from The Ocean has seven and a half beats. The
classic example of 5/4 is Dave Brubeck’s Take Five, but Taylor
Swift’s Closure uses it, too.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1     2     3      4   5   | 1       2   3      4   5   |
vocal: | Yes I   got   your let-ter | Yes I'm   do - ing bet-ter |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Some songs use what’s called “compound meter,”
where not every measure has the same number of beats. The verse
of All You Need Is Love alternates between 4s and 3s. Or you
could say it’s in sevens. The Song That Jane Likes is in 4/4 but
it has a measure of 2 beats every now and then.</p>

<p>Ultimately assigning time signatures is a judgment call based
on what feels natural and what’s most convenient to notate.
It’s a bit like when you’re transcribing speech and you have
to decide where to put periods and commas. There are cases that
could go either way but it’s usually fine. After you spend enough
time in the domain you develop a felt sense of what’s normal.</p>

<p>May you never need to notate The Crunge.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.]]></summary></entry></feed>