<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/dummies/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/dummies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-09T20:34:07-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dummies/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Music theory from dummies</title><subtitle>Talk about. Pop music talk about.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The rest is still unwritten</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The rest is still unwritten" /><published>2022-11-09T10:21:14-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-09T10:21:14-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/09/the-rest-is-still-unwritten.html"><![CDATA[<p>So far we’ve been over how to notate note durations. We accomplished the dubious feat of reading the first two measures of the chorus to Dirty Little Secret by The All-American Rejects.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/d0055b815d31798f4035d0496ede7ebd.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The next measure has a pause before he starts singing again. That’s called a rest.</p>

<h1 id="rests">Rests</h1>

<p>Rest durations are divided the same way note durations are (whole rest, half rest, etc.). The symbols are annoying. Sometimes you can infer them from context clues.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/rest_values.png" alt="Diagram showing rest values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 150px;" /></p>

<p>The set of five horizontal lines, upon which all music is written, is called the <strong>staff</strong>.</p>

<p>The whole and half rest are distinguished by their position with respect to the staff line. The whole rest hangs down from the line, and the half rest pops up, like a top hat. “Half” shares two letters with “hat.” That’s the best I got.</p>

<p>So in the song, we now have a full measure without any notes (four beats, or a whole rest), followed by one quarter rest (one beat) before he starts singing again.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: | 1 &amp; 2 &amp; 3 &amp; 4 &amp; | 1 &amp; 2     &amp; 3    &amp; 4  &amp; |
vocal: |                 |     Don't   tell a-ny   |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Or, nicely typeset:</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/af3f7c4022fd06ac466b5ede334542aa.svg" alt="Next 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>Try tapping out the whole thing. It takes some mental effort at first but once it becomes automatic it’s very fun.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/c7ea4d05e744416296015a5641bc172e.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So far we’ve been over how to notate note durations. We accomplished the dubious feat of reading the first two measures of the chorus to Dirty Little Secret by The All-American Rejects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">They hold no quarter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="They hold no quarter" /><published>2022-11-06T10:52:58-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T10:52:58-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/06/they-hold-no-quarter.html"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re transcribing music, you need to express how long to hold
each note. That’s what rhythm notation is for.</p>

<p>The basic unit of note duration is called a “whole note.” The precise amount of time you hold a whole note depends on a few factors, but if the time signature is 4/4 (and it usually is), a whole note always lasts four beats. A half note is half as long as a whole note (2 beats), a quarter note is half as long as that (1 beat), etc.</p>

<h1 id="how-to-draw">How to draw</h1>

<p>The notation works like hangman: you start with a circle and then
draw more and more extra stuff on it.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/note_values.png" alt="Diagram showing note values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>The circle is called the <strong>note head</strong></li>
  <li>The stick attached to the circle is called a <strong>stem</strong></li>
  <li>The squiggle attached to the stem is called a <strong>flag</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>When you have consecutive notes with flags, it’s conventional to draw them connected together with straight lines (called <strong>beams</strong>).</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/assets/images/beams.jpg" alt="Diagram showing note values." style="width: 100%; max-width: 200px;" /></p>

<h1 id="quarter-notes">Quarter notes</h1>

<p>In 4/4 time, if you tap your foot and count each beat, each tap is 
a quarter note. You can say it out loud while you tap: “1, 2, 3, 4.”</p>

<p>I’ll use Dirty Little Secret a lot because it’s such a simple melody.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: 1    2    3   4
vocal: I'll keep you my
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here’s how you’d formally draw that measure. The little “c” symbol means “common time” (4/4).</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/20d9593b349218e9dbed29e99e9801eb.svg" alt="First measure of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>A quarter note lasts for one beat, so each note in this measure is a quarter note.</p>

<h1 id="eighth-notes">Eighth notes</h1>

<p>If you divide each foot-tap in half, each half has a name:</p>
<ul>
  <li>the <strong>downbeat</strong>: when your foot is on the ground</li>
  <li>the <strong>upbeat</strong>: when your foot is off the ground</li>
</ul>

<p>You count these out loud by adding the word “and”: “1 and 2 and 3 and 4 and.” When you say that, each syllable is one eighth note. Each number is a downbeat, and each “and” is an upbeat.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>count: 1    &amp;   2   &amp;   3   &amp;   4   &amp;   | 1   &amp;   2   &amp;   3   &amp;   4   &amp;
vocal: I'll     keep    you     my        dir-ty  lit-tle se-     cret
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The first four words last 2 eighth notes each. That’s why they’re quarter notes. The syllables of “dirty little” are each half that length, so we write them as eighth notes.</p>

<p><img src="/dummies/lilypond_files/d0055b815d31798f4035d0496ede7ebd.svg" alt="First 2 measures of Dirty Little Secret chorus." class="" style="" /></p>

<p>The last quarter note’s stem goes up instead of down, but the direction doesn’t matter. It just saves visual space to draw it that way, so the stem doesn’t stick way up above the line.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you’re transcribing music, you need to express how long to hold each note. That’s what rhythm notation is for.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">We got the beat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We got the beat" /><published>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</published><updated>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/dummies/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html"><![CDATA[<p>A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is 
somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. 
It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: x    x    x   x  x      x       x  x
vocal: I'll keep you my dir-ty lit-tle se-cret
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A group of beats is called a measure (or, synonymously, a bar).</p>

<p>Most commonly, beats are grouped in groups of 4.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | x    x    x   x  | x      x       x  x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It’s rare for a hip hop song to use any grouping other than 4. 
A standard rap line spans one single four-beat measure, which 
is why rappers refer to lines as “bars.”</p>

<p>When the beats are grouped in fours, we say a song is “in 
4/4 time.” It’s pronounced “four-four” and it is not a fraction
even though it looks like one.</p>

<p>4/4 is an example of a “time signature.” A song’s time signature 
determines how its rhythm will be written. The top number 
indicates the number of beats in each measure. You can ignore 
the bottom number for now.</p>

<p>In 4/4 music with drums, it’s conventional to hit the snare on
beats 2 and 4. So locating the snare can help you get your bearings.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1    2    3   4  | 1      2       3  4    |
snare: |      x        x  |        x          x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>6/8 is the next most common time signature. It groups beats in sixes.
Think of Piano Man, or the verse of Lucy In The Sky.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1   2    3    4    5  6 | 1    2  3 4     5  6 |
vocal: | Pic-ture your-self in a | boat on a river      |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Other time signatures are much less common, so they tickle your
brain when you hear them. Pink Floyd’s Money is in 7/4. The main
riff from The Ocean has seven and a half beats. The
classic example of 5/4 is Dave Brubeck’s Take Five, but Taylor
Swift’s Closure uses it, too.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1     2     3      4   5   | 1       2   3      4   5   |
vocal: | Yes I   got   your let-ter | Yes I'm   do - ing bet-ter |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Some songs use what’s called “compound meter,”
where not every measure has the same number of beats. The verse
of All You Need Is Love alternates between 4s and 3s. Or you
could say it’s in sevens. The Song That Jane Likes is in 4/4 but
it has a measure of 2 beats every now and then.</p>

<p>Ultimately assigning time signatures is a judgment call based
on what feels natural and what’s most convenient to notate.
It’s a bit like when you’re transcribing speech and you have
to decide where to put periods and commas. There are cases that
could go either way but it’s usually fine. After you spend enough
time in the domain you develop a felt sense of what’s normal.</p>

<p>May you never need to notate The Crunge.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.]]></summary></entry></feed>