<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-03T22:32:16-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Music theory from dummies</title><subtitle>Talk about. Pop music talk about.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">We got the beat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="We got the beat" /><published>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</published><updated>2022-11-03T10:37:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/rhythm/2022/11/03/we-got-the-beat.html"><![CDATA[<p>A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is 
somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. 
It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: x    x    x   x  x      x       x  x
vocal: I'll keep you my dir-ty lit-tle se-cret
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>A group of beats is called a measure (or, synonymously, a bar).</p>

<p>Most commonly, beats are grouped in groups of 4.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | x    x    x   x  | x      x       x  x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>It’s rare for a hip hop song to use any grouping other than 4. 
A standard rap line spans one single four-beat measure, which 
is why rappers refer to lines as “bars.”</p>

<p>When the beats are grouped in fours, we say a song is “in 
4/4 time.” It’s pronounced “four-four” and it is not a fraction
even though it looks like one.</p>

<p>4/4 is an example of a “time signature.” A song’s time signature 
determines how its rhythm will be written. The top number 
indicates the number of beats in each measure. You can ignore 
the bottom number for now.</p>

<p>In 4/4 music with drums, it’s conventional to hit the snare on
beats 2 and 4. So locating the snare can help you get your bearings.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1    2    3   4  | 1      2       3  4    |
snare: |      x        x  |        x          x    |
vocal: | I'll keep you my | dir-ty lit-tle se-cret |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>6/8 is the next most common time signature. It groups beats in sixes.
Think of Piano Man, or the verse of Lucy In The Sky.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1   2    3    4    5  6 | 1    2  3 4     5  6 |
vocal: | Pic-ture your-self in a | boat on a river      |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Other time signatures are much less common, so they tickle your
brain when you hear them. Pink Floyd’s Money is in 7/4. The main
riff from The Ocean has seven and a half beats. The
classic example of 5/4 is Dave Brubeck’s Take Five, but Taylor
Swift’s Closure uses it, too.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> beat: | 1     2     3      4   5   | 1       2   3      4   5   |
vocal: | Yes I   got   your let-ter | Yes I'm   do - ing bet-ter |
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Some songs use what’s called “compound meter,”
where not every measure has the same number of beats. The verse
of All You Need Is Love alternates between 4s and 3s. Or you
could say it’s in sevens. The Song That Jane Likes is in 4/4 but
it has a measure of 2 beats every now and then.</p>

<p>Ultimately assigning time signatures is a judgment call based
on what feels natural and what’s most convenient to notate.
It’s a bit like when you’re transcribing speech and you have
to decide where to put periods and commas. There are cases that
could go either way but it’s usually fine. After you spend enough
time in the domain you develop a felt sense of what’s normal.</p>

<p>May you never need to notate The Crunge.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="rhythm" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A beat is one “pulse.” What constitutes a single pulse is somewhat subjective but it’s pretty clear in most cases. It usually corresponds to one intuitive foot-tap.]]></summary></entry></feed>